Finding Aid for Medical School (University of Michigan) records, 1850-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Subordinate Administrative Officers 1929-1998
  - Thomas J. Herrmann, Associate Dean 1960-1977
    Associate Dean Thomas J. Hermann's Series is divided into two subseries. The first subseries (1970-1977) is composed of committee records. Of particular interest are the files of various departmental review and search committees. Included in this category are Anatomy (1972-1973; 1977), Anesthesiology (1973-1975), Biochemistry (1977), Dermatology (1972-1975), Internal Medicine (1973-1975), Neurology (1977) and Otorhinolaryngology (1977). The second subseries (1960-1974) is made up of administrative records. Particularly rich subjects include the Cooperative Michigan Primary Care Preceptor Program (1972-1974), affiliated hospitals (1960-1973, primarily 1969-1973), and the Postgraduate Medicine Program (1969-1972).
    - Committee Records 1970-1977
      - Departmental Review and Search Committees
        - Anatomy
          - 1972-1973
            - Review Report (Box 96)
            - General (Box 96)
          - 1977
            - Candidates
              - Christensen, A. Kent (Box 96)
              - Midgley, A. Rees and Munger, Bryce (Box 96)
              - Yates, Robert D. (Box 97)
              - Others (Box 97)
            - Data Book (Box 97)
            - General (Box 97)
        - Anesthesiology 1973-1975
          - Candidates
            - Cohen, Peter J. (Box 97)
            - Saidman, Lawrence J. (Box 97)
          - Correspondence (Box 97)
          - Informational Materials (Box 97)
          - Interviews with Staff (Box 97)
          - Minutes (Box 97)
          - Reports of Full Committee 1973, 1974 (Box 97)
          - Reports of Subcommittees 1972-1973 (Box 97)
        - Biochemistry 1977
          - General (Box 97)
          - Faculty Comments (Box 98)
        - Dermatology 1972-1975
          - Candidate-Voorhees, John J. (Box 98)
          - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 98)
          - Informational Material (Box 98)
          - Minutes (Box 98)
          - Reports
            - Draft July 1974 (Box 98)
            - Review Undated (Box 98)
            - Interim July 1974 (Box 98)
            - Search September 1974 (Box 98)
        - Internal Medicine 1973-1975
          - Assessment Questionnaire Report (Box 98)
          - Candidates (William N. Kelley and William D. Odell) (Box 98)
          - Correspondence (Box 98)
          - Data Base (Box 98)
          - Informational Materials (Box 99)
          - Outside Consultants (Box 99)
          - Reports June 1974, December 1974 (Box 99)
          - Steering Committee (Box 99)
          - Subcommittees
            - Assessing Current Department Status (Box 99)
            - Forecasting the Future of Academic Internal Medicine (Box 99)
        - Neurology 1977
          - Candidates
            - Long List (Box 99)
            - Short List (Box 99)
            - Negotiations (Box 99)
            - Final Report (Box 99)
          - Correspondence
            - University of Michigan (Box 99)
            - Non University of Michigan (Box 99)
          - Data Book, 3 folders (Box 99)
          - Informational Materials (Box 100)
        - Otorhinolaryngology 1977, 2 folders (Box 100)
      - Other Committees
        - Active Medical Staff 1970-1973, 3 folders (Box 100)
        - Admissions 1970-1972 (Box 100)
        - Dean's Committee 1971-1973 (Box 100)
        - Joint Committee of the State House and Senate Study of the Need for Family Practitioners 1973 (Box 100)
        - Kalamazoo Liaison Committee 1972 (Box 100)
        - Medical Staff Reorganization, Ad Hoc 1970-1971, 2 folders (Box 100)
        - Senior Year Committee
          - 1970 (Box 100)
          - 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 101)
        - Statewide Graduate Medical Education Program Planning 1973 (Box 101)
        - Transplant Committee 1971 (Box 101)
    - Administrative Records 1970-1977
      - Area Health Education Centers, Special Project Grant 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 101)
      - Cooperative Michigan Primary Care Preceptor Program
        - Biographies of Preceptors (Box 101)
        - Grant Planning 1972 (Box 101)
        - Grant Request 1972 (Box 101)
        - Minutes 1972-1974 (Box 101)
        - Miscellaneous 1972-1974, 2 folders (Box 101)
      - Correspondence
        - April-June, 1970 (Box 101)
        - July-September, 1970 (Box 101)
        - October-December, 1970 (Box 101)
        - January-March, 1971 (Box 101)
        - April-December, 1971 (Box 101)
        - 1970-1972 unsorted (Box 101)
      - Faculty Conference on Curriculum 1968-1969 (Box 101)
      - Family Practice
        - Correspondence 1968-1972 (Box 101)
        - Program 1964-1969 (Box 101)
        - Review 1971-1972 (Box 101)
      - Grand Rapids Medical Education Center (Box 102)
        - Establishment 1971 (Box 102)
        - Coordinating Committee 1972 (Box 102)
        - Correspondence 1970-1973 (Box 102)
      - Great Lakes College Association Medical Education Study 1971-1972 (Box 102)
      - Hospital Affiliations
        - Current Status March 8, 1971 (Box 102)
        - Affiliated Hospitals 1972 (Box 102)
        - Hospitals
          - Ann Arbor Veterans 1970-1973 (Box 102)
          - Henry Ford
            - Dearborn Campus Project 1972 (Box 102)
            - Task Force re Affiliation
              - General 1969-1973, 3 folders (Box 102)
              - Minutes 1971-1972 (Box 102)
              - Reports 1972 (Box 102)
              - Background, ca. 1972 (Box 102)
          - Lutheran Hospital (proposed) 1970-1971 (Box 102)
          - Pontiac Medical Education Group 1971-1972 (Box 102)
          - St. Joseph Mercy Hospital
            - General 1971-1973 (Box 102)
            - Task Force re Affiliation (Box 103)
              - Background 1971-1972 (Box 103)
              - General 1972-1973 (Box 103)
              - Minutes 1971-1972 (Box 103)
              - Report 1972 (Box 103)
          - Wayne County General
            - Task Force re Affiliation
              - UM Position 1972-1973 (Box 103)
              - First Draft and Proposed Changes of Policy Statement 1972-1973 (Box 103)
              - Consulting Firm Reports 1972 (Box 103)
              - Working Papers 1972-1973 (Box 103)
              - Medical Committee-Medical Staff Meeting Minutes 1972-1973 (Box 103)
              - Staff Benefits 1972 (Box 103)
              - Department Information 1971-1972 (Box 103)
              - General 1960-1973, 2 folders (Box 103)
      - Intern Matching Program 1972 (Box 103)
      - Intern Resident Placement 1970-1973 (Box 103)
      - Intern-like Program in Grand Rapids 1972 (Box 103)
      - Medical Care Evaluation in Michigan Community Hospitals Project 1971-1972 (Box 103)
      - Medical Resistance Union 1969 (Box 104)
      - Michigan Association for Graduate and Postgraduate Medical Education 1970-1972 (Box 104)
      - Postgraduate Medicine Program
        - Course Schedule 1971-1972 (Box 104)
        - Department Review Committees 1970-1971 (Box 104)
        - Correspondence 1970-1971 (Box 104)
        - General (Box 104)
        - Richards, Robert K., resignation 1970 (Box 104)
        - Session Evaluations 1969-1971, 3 folders (Box 104)
        - Speech March 3, 1971 (Box 104)
      - Student Electives/Career Orientation, ca. 1970-1972 (Box 104)
      - Upper Peninsula Health Education Project 1972 (Box 104)
      - Washtenaw County Cooperative Family Practice Residency
        - General, 2 folders (Box 104)
        - Core Curriculum 1970 (Box 104)
        - Grant 1973 (Box 104)
  - Fred J. Hodges, Assistant to the Dean 1960-1972
    Fred J. Hodges was an assistant to the dean. Hodges bore primary responsibility for the administration of the Michigan Association for Regional Medical Programs (MARMP). These particular documents have been transferred to the Dean's Records Subgroup, Committee and Council Series, where they supplemented the extensive MARMP policy records already found there. The papers that remain in Hodges' series (1960-1972) are primarily personal documents, including a set of memos Hodges sent to the dean (1966-1972).
    - Administrative Committee on Affiliation with Wayne County General Hospital 1960-1966 (Box 104)
    - "Blueprint of Radiology: Unsolicited Views of Outgoing Chairman Fred J. Hodges, 1964" (Box 104)
    - Correspondence 1966-1969 (Box 104)
    - Historical (See also Box 135) (Box 104)
    - Memos to the Dean 1966-1972 (Box 104)
    - Questionnaire from Governor's Office 1968 (Box 104)
    - Speech to Postgraduate Medicine Department November 7, 1968 (Box 104)
    - Vita (Box 104)
  - Walter G. Rice, Director, Office of Medical Center Planning 1961-1975
    Walter G. Rice was the director of the Office of Medical Center Planning, an organization given strong impetus by the Fauri Committee Report. The Rice series is divided into two subseries, an Administrative File (1964-1975) and a Reference File (1961-1975). Of the two, the Reference File is particularly interesting. Arranged chronologically, it gathers together in one place reports, studies, and publications relating to the development of the Medical Center as a whole, as well as documents considering specific developments and problems on hospital hill.
    - Administrative File 1964-1975
      - Affiliated Hospitals 1970-1974 (Box 105)
      - Ambulatory Care Facility
        - Census Review 1964-1971 (Box 105)
        - Proposed Operating Budget December 1965 (Box 105)
      - Animal Research Facility 1973-1974 (Box 105)
      - Building Conditions Study 1970-1974 (Box 105)
      - Capital Financing
        - General 1970-1974 (Box 105)
        - Medical Center 1972-1973 (Box 105)
        - Miscellaneous Studies, ca. 1971 (Box 105)
        - Zugich Study 1972-1973 (Box 105)
      - Capital Outlay Committee (Joint) 1973 (Box 105)
      - Capital Outlay Request 1971-1972 to 1975-1976, 4 folders (Box 105)
        1974-1975 missing
      - Capital Outlay Working File 1975-1976 (Box 105)
      - Circulation of People Study 1973 (Box 105)
      - Clinical Visit Admissions Comparative Report 1948/49-1968/69 (Box 105)
      - College of Pharmacy 1973 (Box 105)
      - Consultants
        - General 1971-1973 (Box 105)
        - Llewelyn-Davies Weeks Forestier-Walker and Bor 1970 (Box 105)
        - Souder, Clark, Griffin and Associates 1974 (Box 105)
      - Coordinator for Physical Planning 1973-1974 (Box 105)
      - Correspondence 1970 (Box 105)
      - Curriculum 1972 (Box 105)
      - Delphi Probe Summary 1973 (Box 105)
      - Department of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education 1972-1974 (Box 105)
      - Family Practice Residency Program in Washtenaw County 1971 (Box 105)
      - Furstenberg Student Center 1970-1972 (Box 105)
      - Greater Detroit Area Hospital Council 1971-1973 (Box 105)
      - Health Professions Education Facilities Survey 1973 (Box 16)
      - Health Sciences Information Center 1966 (Box 16)
      - Health Sciences Libraries 1965-1975 (Box 16)
      - Health Services Research Group 1973-1974 (Box 16)
      - Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation and Related Disorders 1970-1972 (Box 16)
      - Inteflex Program 1972-1974 (Box 16)
      - "Let's Move Group," 1970-1971 (Box 16)
      - Linear Accelerator 1971 (Box 16)
      - Management of Professional Fee Income 1971 (Box 16)
      - Medical Center
        - Administrative Staff 1973 (Box 16)
        - Board-in-Control 1971-1974 (Box 16)
        - Library Annual Reports 1968-1973 (Box 16)
        - Library Grant
          - Correspondence 1974 (Box 16)
          - Application 1974-1975, 2 folders (Box 16)
          - Historical Notes 1966-1974 (Box 16)
          - Background 1961-1966 (Box 16)
        - Parking 1974 (Box 16)
        - Planning Committee 1972 (Box 16)
      - Medical Education 1970-1974 (Box 16)
      - Medical Mailing Service 1972-1974 (Box 16)
      - Medical School 1971-1974 (Box 16)
      - Medical Staff By-laws and Regulations (Proposed) 1973 (Box 107)
      - Michigan
        - Medical Manpower 1973 (Box 107)
        - Medical Schools 1972 (Box 107)
        - Medical Schools Affiliated Hospital 1971 (Box 107)
        - Medical Schools Graduates 1970-1973 (Box 107)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 107)
      - Office of Allied Health Education 1972-1973 (Box 107)
      - Office of Medical Center Planning
        - Issues and Assumptions 1973 (Box 107)
        - Long Range
          - Plan 1972-1973 (Box 107)
          - Plan Draft 1972 (Box 107)
          - Miscellaneous (Box 107)
        - Medical Center
          - Phase I 1974, 2 folders (Box 107)
          - Phase II 1974-1975 (Box 107)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 107)
        - Plan-O-Gram 1971-1972 (Box 107)
        - Planning Essays, ca. 1971 (Box 107)
        - Planning Memoranda 1971-1974 (Box 107)
        - Reports 1967-1972 (Box 107)
        - University of Michigan Functional Resource Analysis (UMFRA) 1972-1974 (Box 107)
      - Plant Extension Committee 1973 (Box 108)
      - Presentations 1973-1974 (Box 108)
      - Psychiatric Facilities Program Outline 1968 (Box 108)
      - Requests for Information 1972-1973 (Box 108)
      - School of Nursing
        - General 1970-1973 (Box 108)
        - Long Range Planning 1975 (Box 108)
      - Scott Turner Geriatric Wing 1973-1974 (Box 108)
      - Simpson Memorial Institute 1974 (Box 108)
      - Site and Access Study 1972-1974 (Box 108)
      - Space Inventory
        - Project 1972-1974 (Box 108)
        - Background 1962-1972 (Box 108)
      - St. Joseph Mercy Hospital 1972-1974 (Box 108)
      - Shirt Sleeves Seven Group 1973 (Box 108)
      - Student Electives Distribution 1970-1971 (Box 108)
      - Teaching Hospitals Subsidies 1969 (Box 108)
      - University Hospital
        - Alternative Sites 1973-1974 (Box 108)
        - Core Hospital Resources 1971 (Box 108)
        - General Divisions 1970-1974 (Box 108)
        - Lutheran Hospital Proposal 1967-1970 (Box 108)
        - Obsolescence 1971-1972 (Box 108)
        - Reuse or Reassignment 1972-1974 (Box 108)
        - Renovation and Remodeling 1970-1974 (Box 108)
    - Reference File 1961-1975
      - 1961
        - Medical Center Planning Report (Box 109)
      - 1962
        - Buildings Under Study (Box 109)
      - 1963
        - Buildings Under Study (Box 109)
        - Medical Science Building, Holabird and Root Architects (Box 109)
        - Projected Traffic Demands of the Medical Center 1980 (Box 109)
      - 1964
        - Emergency Room Study (Box 109)
        - Fuller Parking Alignment Study (Box 109)
        - Medical Science II Grant Applications, 2 folders (Box 109)
        - C. S. Mott Children's Hospital Planning Report (Box 109)
        - Office of the Vice President for Academic Affairs, Plans Under Study for the Growth of the University, 2 folders (Box 109)
      - 1965
        - Analysis of Present and Future Building Area and Volume Classified by Utility Demand Characteristics (Box 109)
        - Buildings Under Study (Box 109)
        - Health Science Information Center
          - General Proposal (Box 109)
          - Library (Box 109)
          - MEDLARS Site Visit (Box 109)
        - Outpatient Procedural Guide (Box 109)
      - 1966
        - Ambulatory Care Center (Volume 1)
        - Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation, Development of Special Capacities
          - University Hospital, Planning and Development Report (Box 109)
      - 1967
        - Buildings Under Study (Box 109)
        - Medical Center Library, Recommendation for Expansion (Box 109)
        - University Hospital Planning Report, 3 folders (Box 109)
      - 1968
        - Burn Center Facility Program Outline (Box 109)
        - Hospital Utilization Review Manual, Beverly C. Payne, ed. (Box 109)
        - University Hospital Study and Advisory (Fauri) Committee (Box 109)
      - 1969
        - Ambulatory Care Sub-System, Roy Penchansky (Box 109)
        - Procedural Guidelines Program Cost Allocation Studies in Medical Centers (Box 109)
        - Hospital Systems Improvement Program: Space Inventory and Utilization (Box 110)
        - Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation, Building, 2 volumes (Box 110)
        - Michigan Department of Public Health, Survey of University Hospital (Box 110)
        - Washtenaw County Medical Care Study Committee Final Report, William G. Hayes (Box 110)
      - 1970
        - Ad Hoc Let's Move Group, Brook Lodge Sequel re Planning (Box 110)
        - Chelsea Community Hospital (Box 110)
        - Emergency Service (Box 110)
        - Integrated Information Systems (Box 110)
        - Medical Center Building Commitments (Box 110)
        - Medical Facilities Survey, Women's Hospital Building (Box 110)
        - Medical School Statistics for AMA Journal 1950-1970 (Box 110)
        - Office of Medical Center Planning (Box 110)
        - University Community Health Service, Recommendation (Box 110)
      - 1971
        - Building Commitments/Major Renovations (Box 110)
        - Office of Medical Center Planning (Box 110)
        - Plan-O-Gram (Box 110)
        - Report on Physician Manpower and Medical Education (Box 110)
        - State Plan for Nursing in Michigan (Box 110)
        - Status Report on Programs of Medical School and Hospital (Box 110)
        - University Hospital Affiliations (Box 111)
        - University Medical Center Building Conditions, 3 volumes (Box 111)
        - University Research Units (Box 111)
      - 1972
        - Advance Planning Committee (1970-1972) (Box 111)
        - Building Data Book (Box 111)
        - Capital Financing of Clinical Facilities (Box 111)
        - Comprehensive Health Care System for the University of Michigan (Carpenter) (Box 111)
        - Final Report 1971-1972 Senior Year Evaluation by Students (Box 111)
        - Guidelines for Distribution (Box 111)
        - Medical Center Library Annual Report (Box 111)
        - Office of Medical Center Planning Staff Meeting Minutes 1970-1972 (Box 111)
        - Department of Pathology; Fifteen Year Report (1956-1971) and Five Year Projection, A. James French (Box 111)
        - Report of the Joint Task Force on Affiliation between St. Joseph Mercy Hospital and UM (Box 111)
        - Selected Planning Office Documents (Box 112)
        - Shirt Sleeve Group, 2 folders (Box 112)
        - University Hospital
          - Feasibility of Bond Issue (Box 112)
          - Organization (Box 112)
          - School (1922-1972) (Box 112)
      - 1973
        - University Hospital, Administrative Quarterly Reports (Box 112)
        - University Medical Center, A Strategy for Renewal (Box 112)
      - 1974
        - Office of Medical Center Planning (Box 112)
        - Patient Activity Reports (1971-1974) (Box 112)
        - Scott Turner Wing and Parkview Renovation, Report of the Planning Committee (Box 112)
        - University Hospital, Identification and Preliminary Evaluation of Site Alternatives (Box 112)
        - University Medical Center Health Sciences Facilities Capital Outlay Budget (Box 112)
      - 1975
        - Medical Campus Library and Resource Center Architectural Program (Box 112)
        - Sites, Utilities and Transportation Study (Box 112)
        - University Medical Center Health Sciences Facilities Capital Outlay Budget Request (Box 112)
  - James A. Taren, Associate Dean 1943-1982
    Associate Dean James A. Taren served as Associate Dean for Educational Affairs. This series (1943-1982) is an artificial one, created to hold long runs of student related materials. In particular the series contains the "Class of" file and student handbooks. The "Class of" material (1943-1944; 1951-1982) contains material on each medical school class. Arranged by class year, most files include a class roster, list of internship assignments, and graduation day exercise material. Student handbooks are official publications of the Medical School giving detailed information about what is expected of the student in a particular year of medical study.
    - "Class of" File
      - 1943-1944, 2 folders (Box 112)
      - 1951-1963, 13 folders (Box 112)
      - 1964-1981, 19 folders (Box 113)
  - Charles A. Votaw, Associate Dean 1929-1977
    Charles A. Votaw was Associate Dean for Curriculum. His series (1929-1977, primarily 1950-1977) has been divided into three subseries: Committee Records, Medical Examination Questions, and Administrative Files. The Committee Records (1948-1977) have extensive material from the Academic Programs Committee (1964-1977), including records of that committee's chairman, James A. Taren (1975-1977), and the Curriculum Committee (1948-1963). The Medical Examination Questions (1929-1974) consists of copies of the tests given to medical students. The Administrative Files include particularly detailed information about affiliated hospitals.
    - "Class of" File
      - 1982 (Box 114)
    - Student Handbooks
      - Junior Year 1978/79-1982/83, 5 volumes (Box 114)
      - Senior Year 1971/72, 1975/76-1982/83, 9 volumes (Box 114)
    - Committee Records
      - Academic Programs
        - Full Committee Minutes
          - January 1964-August 1972 [January 1969-April 1970 missing], 6 volumes (Box 115)
          - September 1972-July 1977, 5 volumes (Box 116)
        - Steering Committee Minutes
          - August-December 1972, 2 volumes (Box 116)
          - January 1973-May 1975 [February-November 1974 missing], 3 volumes (Box 117)
        - James A. Taren, Committee Chair
          - Minutes- January 1975-November 1977, 5 volumes (Box 117)
          - Evaluation and Planning Project 1976 (Box 117)
          - Evaluation and Planning Project 1976 (folder 2) (Box 118)
      - Accreditation 1975, 2 volumes (Box 118)
      - Allied Health Programs 1972-1976, 6 folders (Box 118)
      - Clinical Medicine Program Review 1976 (Box 118)
      - Curriculum
        - 1948-1952
          - General (Box 118)
        - 1952-1953
          - General (Box 118)
        - 1954-1955 (Box 119)
          - General (Box 119)
        - 1955-1956
          - General (Box 119)
          - Minutes (Box 119)
        - 1956-1957
          - General (Box 119)
        - 1958-1959
          - General (Box 119)
        - 1959-1960
          - General (Box 119)
          - Psychiatry (Box 119)
          - Teaching Policies and Practices (1958-1960) (Box 119)
        - 1960-1961
          - General, 2 folders (Box 119)
          - Minutes (Box 119)
          - Quarter System (Box 119)
        - 1961-1962
          - General (Box 119)
          - Curriculum Study (1905-1962) (Box 119)
          - Minutes (Box 119)
        - 1962-1963
          - General (Box 119)
          - Minutes (Box 119)
      - Goals and Objectives 1970-1976
        - Background, 2 folders (Box 119)
        - By-laws/Rules and Regulations of the Medical and Dental Staff 1974 (Box 120)
        - Correspondence (Box 120)
        - Departmental (Box 120)
        - Instructional Goals, Defining (Box 120)
        - Minutes August 1972-1976 [February-December 1973 missing], 6 folders (Box 120)
      - Health and Human Values Task Force 1975
        - Report and Minutes, 2 volumes (Box 120)
      - Honor Code, Ad Hoc Committee to Investigate Alleged Violations 1973, 2 folders (Box 120)
      - Legislative 1976-1977 (Box 120)
      - Student Evaluation (by Faculty) Subcommittee 1973-1974 (1 volume) (Box 120)
      - University Planning Committee on Religion 1972-1973 (Box 120)
    - Medical Examination Questions (Box 121)
      - 1929-1948, 10 volumes; 2 folders (Box 121)
      - 1948-1958, 9 volumes (Box 122)
      - 1958-1964, 7 volumes (Box 124)
      - 1964-1970, 4 volumes (Box 125)
      - 1974-1975, 2 volumes (Box 126)
    - Administrative File
      - Correspondence 1972-1976, 2 folders (Box 126)